[Music]
[Applause]
effective training take one
let's face it it's the wild wild west
out there on social media you got all
these exercise gurus and influencers and
content creators and complete charlatans
and they're all out there dueling and
battling it out as to which exercises
are great and which exercises are not so
great and for the record i don't
understand how people bash exercises
exercises are good to me if you bash and
exercise it shows that you're not a real
trainer it shows that you're one of
those guys who sits behind a computer
and makes stuff up because any real
trainer they love exercise variations
i'm friends with all these real trainers
that own gyms and train real people in
real life we love all the exercises
we're always interested in new
variations those of us who write
programs for lots of people you gotta
keep it interesting it's like this okay
think of a carpenter all right a good
carpenter is gonna have a ton of tools
right now on their tool belt they'll
have the hammer and the screwdriver and
these tools that they use very often
those might be your squats your bench
press your hip thrusts you know your
chin ups but that carpenter will also
have a ton of specialty tools right as a
trainer these are your dual elevated
single leg hip thrust and your kneeling
cable kickback and your knee banded
eccentric accentuated hip thrust you
know those aren't your big rocks but
you're gonna use them throughout the
year a lot same with the carpenter he's
gonna need some specialty saw or sander
or something like that throughout the
year to complete the job you never see a
good carpenter bashing tools you'd never
see a good carpenter be like the hammer
is stupid so to me when a fitness person
bashes and exercise they're giving away
they're a phony they're a fraud they're
a charlatan they don't really train
people they spend their whole day on
social media making things up for this
reason i created an exercise efficiency
guide i wanted to do this for myself
because it's good to categorize things
and form a model but i especially did
this for you i want you guys to be able
to analyze exercise and form your own
opinion and especially not be fooled by
these idiots out there that make up
their own biomechanics so how do we know
if an exercise is effective well they're
different types of clues in my guide
i've broken it down into three
categories of clues all right now each
of these clues provide one piece to the
puzzle but these pieces formulate the
puzzle and they're all important all of
the pieces have flaws and limitations
all right used to be the emg was all
that and lately it's been criticized
people pointing out its limitations but
everything on this list has its
limitations you know musculoskeletal
modeling has its limitations muscle
soreness has its limitations all of the
clues have limitations which is why we
need to rely on multiple cues and lots
of data points to help us hone in on the
truth but no logical person would ever
just choose one or two puzzle pieces and
you see that out there you see some of
these gurus only relying on functional
anatomy or only relying on emg or only
relying on the feel they really should
be taking everything into consideration
and never ignoring any puzzle pieces so
back to this guide the first category is
common sense clues now these are the
most popular clues because they don't
require technology everyone out there
can do an exercise and judge how it
feels you can pay attention to
sensations like soreness or the pump or
the burn everyone out there can analyze
functional anatomy be like okay here are
the lines of the pecs it makes sense
that they do this now the second
category is numerical clues these are
great because they provide numerical
data the feel is all just subjective
it's like i feel this working well but
how do you know if an easy bar curl
compared to a preacher curl compared to
concentration curl you feel all of them
working your biceps very well so how can
we differentiate those exercises and
really examine how they differ and how
they might be beneficial but these clues
require technology they are mostly
utilized by sports scientists who have
the necessary equipment to obtain this
data now this brings us to the final
category longitudinal clues now
longitudinal clues are awesome but they
are the most uncommon due to the time
requirements you know everyday coach or
trainer can't carry out a longitudinal
study they don't have the equipment they
don't have the people they don't have
the time the people carrying out
longitudinal research are mainly
research professors typical semester is
16 weeks long if you have a 12-week
training study this takes up the whole
semester because you have to prepare for
the study carry out the study and then
analyze all the data there are a lot
more dropouts with longitudinal studies
so these are more rare and less common
common sense and numerical clues they
lead to the generation of hypotheses and
the formation of theories but
longitudinal research tests those
hypotheses and theories in a perfect
world experiments would match the
theories they'd go hand in hand that
doesn't always happen now in a perfect
world we would have hundreds of
randomized controlled trials hundreds of
longitudinal studies training studies
testing out every single exercise you
know every exercise the step up the
push-up the inverted row they would all
have a hundred different training
studies on different populations looking
at beginners advanced you know young old
underweight overweight newbies advanced
males females there'd be studies on all
the different variations of that
exercise you know looking at different
program design variables like different
volumes and frequencies and you'd have
so many studies that it would warrant
review papers you know like authors need
to take a look at all the studies and
summarize them because there's so much
to look at unfortunately this is not the
case in strength training research it
will never be the case 300 years from
now it won't be the case because we
don't have the funding that other fields
have and again longitudinal research is
very time consuming it's very expensive
whereas mechanistic data provides
numerical clues those might just take
you a weekend to obtain the data you
might be able to get everything you need
for that study in two sessions so our
field will always be limited by
longitudinal data so in the absence of
training studies we have to rely more on
the common sense and numerical clues
that's why all of these puzzle pieces
fit together and then we update our
beliefs as we gain more knowledge over
time that's the essence of science and
the best exercise for me might not be
the best exercise for you we all have
different anatomies different
physiologies different psychologies
different injury risks different fears
different experiences different
preferences and that's why each of these
clues have an individual component to
them but there's also an average
component like what's best for the
masses versus what's best per individual
and that's why you really need to pay
attention to these clues for yourself so
that you can determine your best
exercises so let's dive right into the
guide looking at the guide you see
common sense clues feel sensation you
know perform a fly all right where do
you feel this stretch where do you feel
the muscle working do you feel it in the
pecs that's what that means burn all
right jewish set with really high reps
and feel where do you feel the burn if i
do a high rep set of curls my biceps
will be burning but do a bunch of sets
with limited rest periods and you'll get
a pump where do you get a pump you know
if you do a bunch of sets of hip thrusts
you get a pump in your glutes if so it's
probably a good glute exercise dom's
that stands for delayed onset muscle
soreness do a bunch of sets of an
exercise and then pay attention to where
you feel sore the next day or the day
after tension okay how can we estimate
tension well there's visual and there's
palpation right if i'm doing a leg
extension and you see my quads
contracting you see all the striations
come out my quads and it's probably good
quad exercise sometimes you can see
people wearing leggings you see their
glutes contract inside the leggings you
can tell it's a good glute exercise but
even more so if you palpate now you can
palpate yourself or you can palpate
other people while they're doing the
lift and you can feel for yourself how
much tension is being generated is the
muscle getting rock hard if so it's
probably a good good exercise for that
muscle functional anatomy these are your
your joint actions and your fiber
directions right you know if you look at
the biceps and you picture the biceps
pulling together it's going to raise the
arm right that's what it would do if you
look at the lines of the pecs you can
probably see that if you want to work
the bulk of the pec fibers you should
probably be
out here is in the in the horizontal
plane now this doesn't always apply but
sometimes you can just look at the
physiques of lifters who who prioritize
a lift for example olympic weight
lifters right they're always doing deep
squats they're doing deep high bar back
squats and they're doing deep front
squats olympic weight lifters have big
quad development and the squat is their
main exercise it's not far-fetched to
assume the squat is good for the quads
and finally discussions with other
lifters coaches trainers you might not
like a certain exercise it's important
to work with other people train other
people and work with other people so
that you can see how other people react
because they have different anatomies
and physiologies now we're moving on to
numerical clues all right there's emg
that stands for electromyography there's
wire and surface emg this tells you the
level of muscle activation there's also
functional mri and this detects fluid
shifts that are associated with
metabolic activity we got ultrasound
which you can use to look at like cell
swelling changes in muscle thickness you
can also use shear wave elastography to
look at muscle stiffness which is
associated with muscle force and tension
you can take biopsies and look at
disturbances to the extracellular matrix
and the z lines within the sarcomere
that's rare but that looks at muscle
damage you can test metabolites like use
lactate strips and test other
metabolites and glycogen depletion to
get an idea of the metabolic stress you
can test your creatine kinase and
myoglobulin levels to see if markers of
muscle damage are elevated you can look
at hormones and peptides for example
testosterone free tests uh cortisol
human growth hormone insulin like growth
factor mechanical growth factor to see
if they're elevated after an exercise
you can look at range of motion all
right the overall range that the joint
goes through or the strain on the muscle
to look at the percentage of muscle
stretch you can take a look at moment
arms and pination angle you know this is
providing numbers to functional anatomy
how much leverage does it have for this
particular joint action what percentage
of the muscle fibers are useful for
force production in this particular
direction so we can perform an exercise
on force plates and look at you know
ground reaction force in the different
directions we can look at power rate of
force development impulse work now we
can look at the force length curves of a
muscle you know how much active tension
and passive tension is generated
throughout the range of motion due to
that muscle specific resting sarcomere
length and moment arms and every muscle
is unique and then we can look at
exercise and look at their torque angle
curves and see how do they line up with
that muscle's inherent force length
curve we can utilize musculoskeletal
modeling which is complex you know it
involves motion cameras and force plates
and sometimes emg to wear all these
markers and electrodes but that's
complex biomechanical stuff you can take
biopsies in a muscle and look at the
acute muscle protein synthesis you can
look at the intracellular signaling this
is rare but you can look at things like
mapk akt the mtor pathway you know
calcium dependent pathways p70 s6k these
give you an indication of is it
stimulating muscle growth and on the
performance form we can look at paper
post activation performance enhancement
if you perform this exercise before an
event like a sprint or a jump does it
enhance the performance or does it not
now i really want to mention here every
one of these may sound amazing but they
all have massive limitations and
drawbacks in another video i filmed i
mentioned these drawbacks and it was
like 40 minutes long so i refilmed this
video so i don't go on and on but trust
me on this they all have massive
limitations one puzzle piece on his own
doesn't tell you the big picture and
finally we move on to the longitudinal
clues with hypertrophy there are a lot
of tools that we can use you can look at
girth with just a tape measure but
that's not highly valid because you can
gain fat and have your girth measures go
up you can use ultrasound you can use
dexa you can use bia bioelectrical
impedance you know we have the bod pod
we have underwater weighing we have skin
fold tests we have ct scans we have mri
which is the gold standard we have
biopsies to look at individual fibers
you can combine modalities like skin
fold plus girth measurements and then
now you have csa cross-sectional area
and now we're moving towards four
component models where you combine some
of these together to make it even more
accurate so those are the tools used to
measure hypertrophy with strength we can
test eccentric concentric or isometric
strength now we can use the force plate
or an isokinetic dynamometer to look at
isometric strength typically the force
plate is used for compound movements in
the dynamometer for single joint
movements we can also use the
dynamometer to test eccentric or
concentric strength but the most common
test of strength are just rep maxes you
know the one rep max you know what's the
most weight that you can squat or bench
press you can also perform more than one
wrap you know three reps five reps and
you can use a regression equation you
know a rep calculator to estimate your
one rep max and on the performance front
with the elderly we tend to look at adls
this stands for activities of daily
living right the sit-to-stand you know
you're sitting you stand up how long did
it take you to go from a sit-to-stand
these are your functional everyday
activities now in sports we tend to look
at force and power in different vectors
right you might look at like a 5 or 10
meter acceleration or a top speed sprint
like 40 meters you can do a vertical
jump you can do a horizontal or a broad
jump you can do different lateral
agility tests and change of direction
tests you can test rotational power in
different ways but this guide represents
all the ways that we can provide clues
as to how effective an exercise is for
different purposes for hypertrophy
strength and performance think of an
exercise you're curious about say the
push-up in a perfect world we'd be able
to take this guide and we'd have surveys
surveys on thousands of lifters for the
common sense clues right we'd have
numerous acute mechanistic studies
providing numerical data for every item
listed on the guide and we'd have
numerous randomized controlled trials
looking at all sorts of things and these
experiments would test those hypotheses
provided by the common sense and
numerical clues and hopefully they would
match each other they would marry just
fine together and we'd have a really
good picture of how good an exercise is
for each purpose that's just not the way
it is in our field strength and
conditioning has limited research
because it's not that important obesity
and cancer research is much more highly
funded these are killing people whether
or not you lift weights or not is not
going to kill you lifting weights can
surely enhance your quality of life and
extend your lifespan but it's not as
critical of a line of research as other
fields so we're never gonna have the
full puzzle we're never gonna have a
perfect puzzle telling us everything we
want to know so we fill in every puzzle
piece we know and then we fill in the
gaps using our best judgment that's how
any logical rational scientific person
would go about it and i might take the
existing puzzle pieces and form this
opinion and it could differ from another
person's opinion but if we're both
scientific we could say yep i see your
point you see my point we need more
research and then we'd come to an
understanding when more research is
available we can agree to disagree but
we both respect each other but that's
not what you see right now
on social media right now like i said in
the beginning of this video it's the
wild wild west and some of these gurus
out there have realized that the
algorithms reward polarization they
reward black and white comments they
like drama they like black and white
they don't like gray so when these guys
bash exercises they gain a following
then that needs to end every exercise is
good for different reasons and you can
use this guide to determine for yourself
how effective it is for your goals all
right that's a wrap thanks for watching
be sure to hit like if you like this
post please leave a comment and tell me
what you think and definitely make sure
you're subscribed thanks for watching
you